Guide to the Shoals Marine Laboratory records, 1966-2000.
Shoals Marine Laboratory records
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Shoals Marine Laboratory records, 1966-2000.
21-48-3866
Shoals Marine Laboratory.
13 cubic feet.
Correspondence, Movie Film, Photographs, Printed Materials, Publications
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes records, film, video and computer files documenting the history of the laboratory and its programs.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
Shoals Marine Laboratory (SML) is dedicated to undergraduate research and education in marine science. Founded in 1966, the program has offered students the unique opportunity to gain hands-on experience in the field for nearly 50 years.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes records, film, video and computer files documenting the history of the laboratory and its programs. The collection houses a variety of documents, some from before SML's founding. This includes newsletters (from 1967-2003), reports on the program, the SML charter, finances, surveys, logs, various publications, correspondences, photographs, boat and house information and contracts, equipment information, and a number of other historical and miscellaneous documents. There are also a number of videos mostly in the form of either VHS or film reel. Some of these are SML oriented, focusing on history or the island, while others are marine biology related, educational videos about whales or other oceanic beings. Also correspondence, including some from John Kingsbury regarding trying to get the lab started and the funding, research, and operations of the lab. Logs of the Research Vessel Wrack and correspondence about how it was acquired.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Kingsbury, John Merriam, 1928-; Shoals Marine Laboratory.; Shoals Marine Laboratory.
Subjects:
Marine biology.; Whales.
Places:
Appledore Island (Me.); Isles of Shoals (Me. and N.H.); Portsmouth (N.H.)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Documents and Correspondence
Series II. Photographs
Series III. Slides
Series IV. Films, Videos, Cassettes
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Documents and Correspondence
  - Misc. Summer Documents, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Misc. Summer Documents, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Misc. Summer Documents, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Misc. Summer Documents, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Misc. Summer Documents, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Misc. Summer Documents, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Misc. Summer Documents, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Misc. Summer Documents, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Misc. Summer Documents, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Misc. Summer Documents, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Misc. Summer Documents, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Misc. Summer Documents, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Robert B. Clark 'FR, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Old Checklists, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - SML Publicity, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Logs, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Newsletters, 1970-1981 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Newsletters, 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Cornell Summer Program in Marine Biology (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Budget Conference, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Star Island Lease Negotiations, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - SML Lease Agreement, 1990s (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Div. of Bio. Science, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - IOS Marine Sanctuary, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Appledore Island - National Historical Site, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Summer Course, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Rel. to Div. of Bio. Science, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Campaign Committee "Early Work", 1960s (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Shoals: Covenants and Properties, 1999-2005 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - The Convenant, 1998-2003 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Negotiation on New Covenant, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Lease with Star, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Pamphlets (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - SML Planning, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Reports on The Program" and Annual Reports, 1966-1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondences, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Viking, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Jere Chase, 1973-1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - SML Bylaws (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Radio and Phone Info., 1990s (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - SML Reorganization Plan, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Star Island Corporation - Appledore Lease (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Survey, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Survey Analysis, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Field Station Survey, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Survey, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Field Program Competitive Survey, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Marine Field Stations With Educational Programs Survey, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Alumni Sheets, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Alumni Sheets, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Vicarious Shoalers - Lists, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Celia's Garden - SML History (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - G. Boden's Vascular Flora, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Misc. Publications, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Barnacles and Flagpole (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "Barnacles" Marian Wood - 1982 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - NSF - Equipment (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - NSF - Equipment (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Misc. Correspondences, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - NSF - Instructional Equipment (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Section VIII - List of Publications (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Misc. Finances, 1990s (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Misc. Correspondences, 1990s (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - SML Finances, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - SML Finances, 1990s (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Misc. Documents, 1990s (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Misc. Documents, 1990s (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Old Scope Invoices, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Appledore Times, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Newsletters, 1967-1986 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Appledore Times, 1987-1996 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Newsletter - Backissues, 1974-1982 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Misc. Newsletters, 1974-2003 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Star Island Summer Program, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "Report on Establishment of a Cornell Marine Station", 1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - SML - Council/Charters (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Duck Island (Nature Conservatory), 1970s (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - SML - General, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - SML Alumni, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Early Years SML - Annual Report, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Historic Landmarks, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - SML History, 1946-1966 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - SML History, 1966+ (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - NECCRF "Proq/spec/vis", 1970s (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - NECCRF "Proq/spec/vis", 1970s (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - History and Present Circumstances, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Appledore Times Planning, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Isles of Shoals, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Books on I.O.S., Appledore, and SML, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Transect History Docs, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Jack Kingsbury Docs, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - SML Charter, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Useful References- Isles of Shoals, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - ISHRA, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - ISHRA Members, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - SML Council, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - SML Council, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - SML Council, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - SML Council, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - SML Council, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - SML Council, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Maps (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - NECCRF Booklets and More (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Misc. Flyers (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - "The Vascular Flora of Appledore Island", 1977 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "CT Hubbard, Brauna, Johnson", 1982 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Tidal Benchmarks, 1950-1978 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Contruction Photos (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - SML Class Lists and Photos, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Herb Jackson Photos, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Garden Photos, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Appledore Sampler, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Gunnhouse - Vet, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Misc. Documents, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Misc. Documents, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Misc. Documents, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Misc. Documents, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - SML Historical, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - UNH - Council (SML), 1990s (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - UNH Covenant, 1990s (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - New Boat - Critical Information, 2000-2001 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Boats, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - New Boat, 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - New Boat, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - New Boat - Correspondence, 1998-2000 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Boat Designs, 1990-2000 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Kingsbury House, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Kingsbury House, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - "House - Most Recent", 2000 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - PAR, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Dock in Portsmouth, 1995-1998 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - 25k - Cornell, 1996-1998 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Wastewater Treatment, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Annual Reports - Academic (Bound folder), 1966-1979 (Box 4)
  - Budgets, Fiscal Reports and Analyses (Bound folder), 1971-1975 (Box 4)
  - Appledore Newsletters (Bound), 1970-1981 (Box 4)
  - Business cards (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Programs, 1940-2005 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Hyoid Bone literature (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Postcard and note card samples (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - SML Endowment Campaign Binder, 1992 (Box 7)
  - "Unfiled Documents - Xeroxed Materials Primarily" - Bound Notebook (Box 7)
  - Financial and donor correspondence, brochures, newsletters, and reports, 1970-1990 (Box 14)
  - Reports, records, and correspondence, 1960-2000 (Box 15)
  - Blueprints, correspondence, administrative papers, and course materials, 1970-2010 (Box 16)
  - Annual reports, newsletters, and brochures (Box 17)
  - Administrative files, log books, Wrack information (Box 18)
  - Course material and correspondence (Box 19)
- Series II. Photographs
  - Photo albums (Box 20)
  - Photographs and course report scrapbook, 1979 (Box 8)
  - Photographs for newsletter, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Old photographs from C. George (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous backup coverage (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - People and miscellaneous (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - People (Box 8, Folder 5-19)
  - Facilities, 1984-1987 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Lab work, 1984-1987 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Scenery (Box 8, Folder 22-24)
  - Boats (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Boats and people (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Whales and seals, 1984-1985 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Buildings and people, 1984-1985 (Box 8, Folder 28-30)
  - Miscellaneous, 1991-1993 (Box 8, Folder 31-35)
  - Scuba, 1980s (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Panoramas, 1990s (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Birds, 1969-1985 (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Landscapes, people (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - Scrapbook pages, pre-1975 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Intertidal (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Negatives (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Appledore (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous people and buildings, 1984-1985 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Negatives, Tuttle Birthday, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Food cooking, 1984-1985 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Kingsbury, 1980s (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Birds, 1980s, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Additional Prints, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Ollie's photographs, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - George Sylvester photographs, 1984-1990 (Box 9, Folder 13-16)
  - Prints by Kenn and Susan Marash, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - George Sylvester photographs, 1984-1990 (Box 9, Folder 18-23)
  - George's "Specials" (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Celia's Garden, 1979-1982 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Appledore, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Appledore photographs and programs, 1907, 1980s (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Ghostwriter, 1991-1992 (Box 10, Folder 3-4)
  - Ghostwriters negatives, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Sampling, Boats (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Organisms (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Laboratory (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 10, Folder 9-11)
  - Miscellaneous Pre-1975 (Box 10, Folder 12-14)
  - Star Island (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Ollie's photographs, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Group shots (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Saint Croix (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Sylvester negatives, photographs, 1980s (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Buildings and facilities (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Isle of Shoals (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Shoals photo collection negatives, photographs (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Photograph scrapbook, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - January trip, Brewster's shower, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Kingsbury House dedication, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - The wrack (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Aerials (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - Whales (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Birds, Shrimp (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Photographs from Alumni magazine (Box 13, Folder 24)
- Series III. Slides
  - Appledore, Westward, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1966-1984 (Box 11, Folder 2-6)
  - Thomas Stewart (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Ollie's, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Slide sets and duplicates (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Island photos, 1984-1987 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Westward, Boats, Lab Boats (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Warren Potash (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Summer, 1996 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Neil D. Troost, with photographs and correspondence (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1966-1984 (Box 12, Folder 2-3)
  - Individual photographers (Box 12, Folder 4-5)
  - Isles of Shoals (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Facilities, People (Box 12, Folder 7-8)
  - Harelstad (Box 11, Folder 9-11)
  - Weekend, 1997 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Steven Barnett, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Class pictures, 1966-1973 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Kingsbury construction, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Aerial Portsmouth Harbor (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - L Bush (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Whale Watching (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Cormorant Building (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Biological Sciences Final Drawings (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Adapts PK, Seatable Aquarium, Hertz, Neuro (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Inside Hewitt (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Unlabelled (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Moga (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Paul's pictures, storm, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Chris Bag Dono (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - Aerials, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 13, Folder 1-4)
  - Ed's Winter Slides, 2002 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Founder's Hall, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Fuel Tank Pad, 1996 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Dave Hanauer (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Shrimp, 1986-1987 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Minke Skeleton project (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Organisms, habitat (Box 13, Folder 12-13)
  - Shoals, 1968-1973 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Ken and Susan Marash (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Unlabelled (Box 13, Folder 25)
- Series IV. Films, Videos, Cassettes
  - "SML Casual Version", 5548 (Box 5)
  - "SML", 1986; 5549 (Box 5)
  - "Shoals Promo Tape", 1989; 5550 (Box 5)
  - "Waterways: Links to the Sea", 5551 (Box 5)
  - "Shoals Marine Lab", 5552 (Box 5)
  - "Shoals Marine Lab - Student", 5553 (Box 5)
  - "Shoals Marine Lab", 5554 (Box 5)
  - "Summary MetLife Airship Flights", August 6-15, 1993; 5555 (Box 5)
  - "Shoals Marine Lab Student video", 5556 (Box 5)
  - "Shoals Marine Lab Donor Video", 5557 (Box 5)
  - "Shoals Marine Laboratory", 1986; 5558 (Box 5)
  - "UW Research", 1992; 5559 (Box 5)
  - Hagfish Tape, 5560 (Box 5)
  - "Out and About Show #111", 5561 (Box 5)
  - "3 - Daily Backup B", 5562 (Box 5)
  - "The Isles of Shoals - A Profile" Magnetic Tape Video, 5563 (Box 5)
  - "Christene's Dataframe", 1991; 1 (Box 5)
  - "Annelida - Reel I", 229 (Box 5)
  - "Annelida - Reel II", 230 (Box 5)
  - "Annelida - Reel III", 231 (Box 5)
  - "Personal Kingsbury", 1978; 232 (Box 5)
  - "Shoals Film Copy 2", 233 (Box 5)
  - "IMS", 1974; 234 (Box 5)
  - "Introduction to Marine Science", 1974; 235 (Box 5)
  - "Shoals Marine Lab", 236 (Box 5)
  - "Reproduction in Skate", April, 1967; 237 (Box 5)
  - "The Nervous System - Part II" [sic], 238 (Box 5)
  - "Crustacea", 239 (Box 5)
  - "Isles of Shoals, Shoals Film Copy", 240 (Box 5)
  - Untitled Film, 241 (Box 5)
  - Untitled Film, 242 (Box 5)
  - "History of the Isle of Shoals Marine Lab Film", 704 (Box 5)
  - "Island History Movie", 243 (Box 6)
  - "Mammals of the Sea", 1980; 244 (Box 6)
  - "In Search of the Bowhead Whale - Reel I", 245 (Box 6)
  - "In Search of the Bowhead Whale - Reel II", 246 (Box 6)
  - "Echinodermata", 247 (Box 6)
  - "SML and Activities, Algae - Isle of Shoals", 248 (Box 6)
  - "The Humpback Whale: Summer - A Time For Feeding", 249 (Box 6)
  - "The Humpback Whale: Winter - A Time For Singing", 250 (Box 6)
  - "The Whale", 1981; 251 (Box 7)
  - "The Undersea World of Jacques Cousteau: Whales", 252 (Box 7)
  - "Coelenterata I + II", 253 (Box 7)
  - "Mollusca", 254 (Box 7)
  - "Take Two - From The Sea", 255 (Box 7)
  - "Dept. of History of Art - Corbusier: Designs for Harvard - Lease Print", 256 (Box 7)
  - Shoals Marine Lab- Student, V-10251 (Box 20)
  - Right Whales and the Prudent Mariner (16 minute VHS English Version), 1999; V-10252 (Box 20)
  - Shoals Marine Lab- Student, V-10253 (Box 20)
  - Imagine Yourself at UNH: A Community of Learners, V-10254 (Box 20)
  - Shoals Marine Lab- Student Video, V-10255 (Box 20)
  - Shoals Marine Lab- Student Video, V-10256 (Box 20)
  - Shoals Marine Lab- Student, V-10257 (Box 20)
  - Shoals Marine Lab- Student, V-10258 (Box 20)
  - Shoals Marine Lab- Student, V-10259 (Box 20)
  - Shoals Marine Lab- Student, V-10260 (Box 20)
  - Shoals Marine Lab- Student, V-10261 (Box 20)
  - Shoals Marine Lab- Student, V-10262 (Box 20)
  - Shoals Marine Lab- Tape #2, V-10263 (Box 20)
  - Shoals Marine Lab- Tape #6, V-10264 (Box 20)
  - Shoals Marine Lab- Tape #8, V-10265 (Box 20)
  - Shoals Marine Lab- Tape #9, V-10266 (Box 20)
  - Shoals Marine Laboratory: Celebrating 25 Years of Excellence in Marine Education, V-10267 (Box 20)